A Guide to the Virginius Dabney Collection 1941-1947
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Virginius Dabney Collection, 1941-1947
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7690-a
This collection consists of 14 boxes of materials.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was acquired as a gift.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains extensive correspondence, ca. 1930 to 1968, carried on by Dabney as editor of the Richmond Times-Dispatch, in his personal, life, and as a Pulitzer Prize- winning author. Other materials deal with his books such as Below the Potomac, The Dry Messiah, and Liberalism in the South, and much useful material collected as research material for these books is present. There is extensive material on the American Society of Newspaper Editors which Dabney served in various capacities including president. A great deal of useful material on race relations, the African American, the N.A.A.C.P., etc., is present. Recent political history of Virginia is strongly represented in Dabney's correspondence as editor of Virginia's leading newspaper, and in his personal correspondence with figures such as Senator A. Willis Robinson, Francis Pickens Miller, and Senator Carter Glass.
Contents List
- Materials Relating to his "New South" Lectures and his book Below the Potomac.
  - "I New South Reviews & Letters--'Below the Potomac'"(pt. 1) 1941-1942, ca. 100 items (Box 1)
  - "I New South Reviews & Letters--'Below the Potomac' (pt. 2) 1941-1942, ca. 100 items (Box 1)
  - "New South I" (pt. 1) 1941, ca. 150 items (Box 1)
  - "New South I" (pt. 2) 1941, ca. 125 items (Box 1)
  - "II New South" (pt. 1) 1941-1942, ca. 75 items (Box 1)
  - "II New South" (pt. 2) 1941-1942, ca. 125 (Box 1)
  - "II New South" (pt. 3) 1941-1942, ca. 100 items (Box 1)
  - "II New South" (pt. 4) 1941-1942, ca. 150 items (Box 1)
  - "III New South" (pt. 1) 1942-1944, ca. 35 items (Box 1)
  - "The New South" (pt. 2) 1942-1943, ca. 35 items (Box 1)
    Correspondence with Joseph W. Allen of D. Appleton-Century Company
  - "III The New South" (pt. 3) 1942-1943, ca. 100 items (Box 2)
    Correspondence with John L. B. Williams of D. Appleton-Century Company
  - "The New South" (pt. 4) 1945-1952, ca. 25 items (Box 2)
- Materials relating to Colonial Williamsburg
  - Inst. Early American History and Culture, Dr. Bridenbaugh, Dir. 1946-1947, ca. 85 items (Box 2)
  - (Box 2)
  - Colonial Williamsburg, Inc. 1941-1946, ca. 20 items (Box 2)
- Speaking Engagements, 1944-1946
  - Speaking Engagements 1946, ca. 150 items (Box 2)
  - Speaking Engagements (pt. 1) December 1944-1945, ca. 150 items (Box 2)
  - Speaking Engagements (pt. 2) 1947, ca. 150 items (Box 2)
- Materials relating to the Saturday Review
  - Article-- Saturday Review of Literature(pt. 1) 2/24/45, ca. 100 items (Box 2)
  - Article-- Saturday Review of Literature(pt. 2) 2/24/45, ca. 50 items (Box 2)
- Materials relating to African Americans and Segregation
  - Commission on Interracial Cooperation, Rev. Thomas C. Allen, Dir. 1943-1947, ca. 65 items (Box 3)
  - Pittsburgh Courier Colored Newspaper 1944-1945, ca. 20 items (Box 3)
  - Race Relations, Magazines-Newspapers-Etc. 1944, 1 item (Box 3)
  - Race Relations (pt. 1) 1944-1945, ca. 50 items (Box 3)
  - Race Relations (pt. 2) 1945-1946, ca. 50 items (Box 3)
  - Segregation 1944-1945, ca. 20 items (Box 3)
  - Southern Conference for Human Welfare 1944-1946, ca. 15 items (Box 3)
  - "Flat Hat"--(Race Issue) 1945, ca. 12 items (Box 3)
    William and Mary College publication
  - "Is the South that Bad?"--Article appearing in Saturday ReviewApril 13, 1946, ca. 40 items
  - Meyer Award-African American Newspapers 1947, ca. 35 items (Box 3)
  - Booker T. Washington Memorial Birthplace, S.J. Phillips, President 1947, ca, 60 items (Box 3)
  - Southern Regional Council (pt. 1) 1947, ca. 100 items (Box 4)
  - Southern Regional Council (pt. 2) 1944-1947, ca. 100 items (Box 4)
- Material relating to Various Anti-Discrimination Organizations
  - Edward L. Bernays Award--George E. Harris, Executive Secretary 1944-1945, 34 items (Box 4)
  - Council for Democracy 1941-1946, ca. 100 items (Box 4)
  - Freedom House 1942-1946, 13 items (Box 4)
  - FEPC Letters and Editorials 1945-1946, 31 items (Box 4)
  - Virginia Committee on Constitutional Rights 1946, 6 items (Box 4)
  - Southern Regional Council (pt. 1) 1947, ca. 100 items (Box 4)
  - Southern Regional Council (pt. 2) 1944-1947, ca. 125 items (Box 4)
  - National Conference of Christians and Jews, Inc.; Mrs. Blanche M. Hobbs 1945-1947, ca. 100 items (Box 4)
- Material relating to Various International Affairs and World Government Groups
  - Citizens Council for the United Nations 1943, 2 items (Box 4)
  - Council on International Organization, Dr. F.W. Burnham, Chairman 1943-1945, 15 items (Box 4)
  - League of Nations Association, Inc., Clark M. Eichelberger, Director 1944-1945, 5 items (Box 4)
  - International Editorial Board of World Gov't. News, Inc. 1946, 7 items (Box 4)
  - Committee to Study the Organization of the Peace 1946, 13 items (Box 4)
  - Americans United for World Organization 1944-1947, ca. 100 items (Box 5)
  - Southern Council on International Relations, Keener C. Frazer, Director 1946-1947, 19 items (Box 5)
- Materials relating to Public Information Agencies during and after World War II
  - Office of War Information, Basic News Division, Theodore Kaghan, Chief 1943-1944, 8 items (Box 5)
  - Correspondence Panels Section--Office of War Information 1944-1945, 35 items (Box 5)
  - Correspondence Panels, E.G. Herzog 1945-1946, 20 items (Box 5)
  - Writer's War Board 1944, 1946, 14 items (Box 5)
  - Richmond Public Forum, Aubrey H. Straus 1942-1947, 54 items (Box 5)
- Material relating to the American Society of Newspaper Editors
  - American Society of Newspaper Editors 1946-1947, ca. 125 items (Box 5)
  - American Society of Newspaper Editors(pt. 2) 1947, 4 items (Box 5)
  - ASNE--Committee editorial page discussion convention, 1947, ca. 75 items (Box 5)
- Materials relating to Russian Relief during and after World War II
  - Russian War Relief Committee 1943-1944, 7 items (Box 5)
  - American Society for Russian Relief 1945-1946, 7 items (Box 5)
- Materials relating to World War II and its Aftermath
  - Richmond Citizens Navy Committee, Norman L. Flippen, Chr. 1942-1944, 16 items (Box 5)
  - Williamsburg War Board 1944, 16 items (Box 5)
  - Disabled American Veterans, Percy C. Magnus, Chr. 1944, 10 items (Box 5)
  - Compulsory Military Training 1945, 10 items (Box 5)
  - Victory Fund Campaign 1942-1946, ca. 25 items (Box 5)
  - Westbrook Pegler 1944-1946, ca. 50 items (Box 5)
  - War Memorial, letters and editorials 1946, 9 items (Box 5)
  - War Finance Committee of Virginia Bonds 1945-1946, 35 items (Box 5)
- Materials relating to Richmond and Virginia Public Projects
  - Westwood Park Project 1946, 8 items (Box 6)
  - Library Board 1944, 1946, 1947, ca. 25 items (Box 6)
  - Barter Theatre 1944-1947, ca. 35 items (Box 6)
  - Gloucester-Yorktown Bridge 1947, 8 items (Box 6)
- Materials relating to Public Charities
  - Virginia Tuberculosis Association, Miss Ellen Smith, Pres. 1946, 11 items (Box 6)
  - Virginia Cancer Foundation 1941-1947, 53 items (Box 6)
- Materials relating to the Episcopal High School Campaign
  - II Episcopal High School Campaign (pt. 2), Branch Spalding, Dir. 1944-1946, ca. 100 items (Box 6)
  - II Episcopal High School Campaign (pt. 2), Branch Spalding, Dir. 1946, ca. 125 items (Box 6)
  - III Episcopal High School Campaign, Branch Spalding, Dir. 1946-1947, ca. 100 items (Box 6)
- Correspondence with Individuals
  - Applications 1944-1946, 18 items (Box 6)
  - Jacob Billikopf 1945, ca. 35 items (Box 6)
  - Bilden, Rudiger-InterAmerican Regional Institute, University of Virginia 1944-1946, 7 items (Box 6)
  - Darden, Colgate W. Jr. June 27, 1946, ca. 25 items (Box 6)
  - Graves, John Temple II 1941-1946, ca. 30 items (Box 7)
  - Hall, Joseph F., Lawyer n.d., 4 items (Box 7)
  - Herrmann, A.H. 1946, ca. 10 items (Box 7)
  - Dr. J. Shelton Horsley 1945-1946, ca. 20 items (Box 7)
  - Requests for Editorial Contributions 1946, 11 items (Box 7)
  - Hutchinson, M.A. 1946, 6 items (Box 7)
  - Kilpatrick, Carroll 1942-1947, ca. 20 items (Box 7)
  - Lestor Markel, Sunday Editor NY Times--Watchtoner 1943-1947, ca. 50 items (Box 7)
  - Miller, Helen Hill 1942-1947, ca. 40 items (Box 7)
  - Dr. Sidney S. Negus 1944-1947, ca. 30 items (Box 7)
  - Haydn S. Pearson 1944-1946, ca. 30 items (Box 7)
  - Plunkett, Moss A. 1943-1946, ca. 60 items (Box 7)
  - Joseph Reed Routten 1944-1946, ca. 35 items (Box 7)
  - Edward R. Stettinus 1947, ca. 75 items (Box 7)
  - Tucker, Bishop H., St. George Comm. Just and Durable Peace 1942, 2 items (Box 7)
  - Dr. Robert H. Tucker 1944-1947, ca. 60 items (Box 7)
  - Wood, Kenneth C. 1943-1946, ca. 20 items (Box 7)
- Correspondence
  *Note: Correspondence Files A-C were not included by Mr. Dabney in this collection.
  - D (pt. 1) 1946-1947, ca. 125 items (Box 8)
  - D (pt. 2) 1945-1946, ca. 150 items (Box 8)
  - E 1945-1947, ca. 110 items (Box 8)
  - F 1945-1947, ca. 150 items (Box 8)
  - G (pt. 1) 1944, 1946-1947, ca. 100 items (Box 8)
  - G (pt. 2) 1946-1947, ca. 100 items (Box 9)
  - G (pt. 3) 1945-1946, ca. 75 items (Box 9)
  - G (pt. 4) 1944-1946, ca. 100 items (Box 9)
  - H (pt. 1) 1945-1947, ca. 100 items (Box 9)
  - H (pt. 2) 1946-1947, ca. 125 items (Box 9)
  - H (pt. 3) 1945-1946, ca. 75 items (Box 9)
  - H (pt. 4) 1945, ca. 75 items (Box 9)
  - I-J (pt. 1) 1946-1947, ca. 75 items (Box 10)
  - I-J (pt. 2) 1945-1946, ca. 75 items (Box 10)
  - K (pt. 1) 1946-1947, ca. 100 items (Box 10)
  - K (pt. 2) 1945, ca. 125 items (Box 10)
  - L (pt. 1) 1946-1947, ca. 100 items (Box 10)
  - L (pt. 2) 1945-1946, ca. 100 items (Box 10)
  - M (pt. 1) 1947, ca. 100 items (Box 11)
  - M (pt. 2) 1946-1947, ca. 150 items (Box 11)
  - M (pt. 3) 1945-1946, ca. 100 items (Box 11)
  - M (pt. 4) 1945, ca. 75 items (Box 11)
  - N-O (pt. 1) 1943-1947, ca. 75 items (Box 11)
  - N-O (pt. 2) 1945-1946, ca. 125 items (Box 11)
  - P (pt. 1) 1946-1947, ca. 75 items (Box 12)
  - P (pt. 2) 1945-1946, ca. 75 items (Box 12)
  - P (pt. 3) 1944-1945, ca. 60 items (Box 12)
  - R (pt. 1) 1946-1947, ca. 75 items (Box 12)
  - R (pt. 2) 1945-1946, ca. 75 items (Box 12)
  - S (pt. 1) 1946, ca. 115 items (Box 12)
  - S (pt. 1) 1944-1947, ca. 115 items (Box 13)
  - S (pt. 2) 1944-1946, ca. 115 items (Box 13)
  - S (pt. 3) 1944-1946, ca. 65 items (Box 13)
  - S (pt. 4) 1945, ca. 50 items (Box 13)
  - T 1945-1947, ca. 135 items (Box 13)
  - U-V 1944-1947, 80 items (Box 13)
  - W (pt. 1) 1947, ca. 80 items (Box 14)
  - W (pt. 2) 1945-1946, primarily 1946, ca. 100 items (Box 14)
  - W (pt. 3) 1945-1946, ca. 75 items (Box 14)
  - W (pt. 4) 1944-1945, ca. 100 items (Box 14)
  - X, Y, Z 1945-1947, ca. 80 items (Box 14)